<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Harshit Joshi</title>
    <link>/index.html</link>
    <description>Recent content on Harshit Joshi</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language><atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tags</title>
      <link>/tags/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tags/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
, 15 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2021/02/professional-programmer-the-clean-coder/</guid>
      <description>In The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers, legendary software expert Robert C. Martin introduces the disciplines, techniques, tools, and practices of true software craftsmanship. This book is packed with practical advice–about everything from estimating and coding to refactoring and testing. It covers much more than technique: It is about attitude.
In this article, I have tried to summarize key insights from the book, carefully picking key advices from each chapter.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Personal Website 101</title>
      <link>/posts/2019/11/personal-website-101/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 03 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/posts/2019/11/personal-website-101/</guid>
      <description>Motivation There is no need to explain the benefits of personal website or a porfolio site, still, I would note down some:
 Personal Branding Blog Space Makes you discoverable on internet One stop resume which works for you Helps you learn new skills while building  Tech Stack  Hugo Static Site Builder Plenty of themplates available at Hugo Themes Hosting at Github Pages Domain from Godaddy  Steps  First learn the basics of Hugo and how it works by following Hugo Quickstart Guide Once somewhat comfortable with Markdown and Hugo, choose a template/theme for your site You can create your custom theme as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About</title>
      <link>/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/about/</guid>
      <description>Hi, I&amp;rsquo;m Harshit Joshi - Software Engineer based in California, USA. I have 4+ years of professional experience and currently working at Amazon Alexa.
Book Recommendations  The Clean Coder: A Code of Conduct for Professional Programmers - Robert Martin  Interests (In no particular order)  Deep Learning AI Software Developement Operational Excellence Design Patterns  </description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
